Gurmanpreet Kaur Grewal

Toronto, Ontario

Contact No.: +1 4379873711
Email: ggurman20@gmail.com

OBJECTIVE

Skilled professional with **one year** of experience in **web development**. Enthusiastic, detail-oriented, highly motivated, hardworking, and knowledgeable individual with a true passion for the software industry. Looking for a **full-time position** as Software Developer or Web Developer where I can use my skills and knowledge for the growth of the company.

HIGHLIGHT OF SKILLS

- Hands-on experience with MERN Stack (MongoDB, Express, React, Node).
- Well-developed knowledge of frontend and backend emerging technologies like React, NodeJS, and JavaScript (ES6).
- Working knowledge of HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, jQuery, ReactJS, NodeJS, Php, UI development and learning SASS.
- Understanding of use of NPM libraries and Bootstrap.
- **RESTful APIs** using **Node** at the backend.
- Designing and developing Responsive and user-friendly websites while keeping in mind Web Accessibility.
- Debugging using browser developer tools in Chrome, Firefox.
- Calling APIs, extracting data, and testing using **Postman**.
- Proficient in MySQL and MongoDB (Database Management).
- Having knowledge of building project using **Php**, **MySQL** database, **PhpMyAdmin**, and using **Apache** on **XAMPP**.
- mobile application development using **Android** native tools.
- Version Control using GIT and hands-on experience with GitHub.
- Website hosting on Heroku, firebase, GoDaddy.
- knowledge of Unit Testing best practices and tooling by using Jest, React testing library.
- Worked with project management/issue tracking tools like **Jira**, **Trello**.
- Knowledge of AGILE Software development life cycle (SDLC) and participate in daily stand-ups, and sprint retrospectives, and complete two-week sprints.
- Solid understanding and practical implementation of the fundamentals of programming including object-oriented programming (oops).
- Done few projects with AngularJS.
- Developing websites enriched with user experience in terms of performance, security, stability, and quality.
- Understanding of programming base concepts like loops, conditional statements, functions, exception handling, etc.
- Strong written/spoken communication skills, excellent team player, self-motivated and excited to learn modern technologies.
- Worked with other languages like Java, Angular.js, Android, C++, C#, ASP.Net, Visual Studio.

• Developed website in **WordPress** using **WooCommerce**.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

WEB DEVELOPER (Punjab Agricultural University, India)

October 2019 - August 2020

- Worked on web application using **ReactJS**, **CSS3**, **JavaScript (ES6)**, and **firebase** for National Agricultural Higher Education Project CAAST-SNRM.
- Designed front-end using **React** (advanced JavaScript library) to display information about CAAST-SNRM project and Soil Science Department.
- Worked on **responsiveness** of website for all devices by using **media queries**.
- Used **bootstrap** (4.4.1) library in connection with **CSS3** for easy and scalable styling of the website.
- Used JavaScript and jQuery to manipulate UI elements.
- Worked on embedding **iFrame** for google maps.
- Designed a database in firebase to store the information.
- Gained experience of using **GitHub** for collaboration and version control.
- Deployment on **GoDaddy.**
- Worked on cross browser compatibility of the website (Chrome, Firefox & Edge).
- Identified and provided efficient suggestions regarding technical issues.
- Followed general debugging techniques to figure out common issues a website may have.

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

(Punjab Technical University, India)

August 2016 – October 2019

- Taught core technical subjects integrated by Punjab Technical University in their syllabus such as
- Programming for Problem-Solving,
- Object-Oriented Programming (C++),
- Data Structure,
- Operating System
- to Indian as well as international students from Uganda, Yemen, Zimbabwe, Gambia, and Sudan.
- By using various teaching aids such as demonstrations, assignments, discussions, and case studies, has taught students in an effective manner.
- Giving assignments to students and assessing their work according to pre decided rubrics.
- Maintaining students' performance record for continuous evaluation.
- Performed the tasks of maintaining College websites as a web developer along with teaching.

PROJECTS

My Portfolio

- https://gurman.netlify.app/
- Designed in React and deployed on Netlify.
- Explore about me and my various projects in ReactJS, NodeJS, MEAN Stack, JavaScript.

Drapsio (MERN Stack)

http://drapsio.herokuapp.com/

- Developed an e-commerce website using **MERN** Stack and deployed on **Heroku**.
- Designed a responsive frontend using React library to display a list of products to the user.
- Designed a database in MongoDB to store information about products, orders, and users.
- Created REST API with routes to display the data using Node and Express.
- Implemented authentication to allow users to create accounts and admin to update the inventory with **JSON** web Token (JWT).
- Displayed information about each product with React components consuming the REST API.
- Stripe API is used to process the payment.
- Collaborated as a team using the **AGILE** methodology and **GITHUB** for version control.

Instagram clone

https://instagram-clone-react-546c6.web.app/

- Developed Instagram clone using ReactJS and firebase
- Designed front-end using **ReactJS** to display a list of posts along with comments on posts.
- Designed a database in **firebase** to store information about users' login details and posts, which users will post in their account.

ReactFlix - (Netflix Clone)

https://reactflix-41834.web.app/

- Developed using React and deployed on Firebase.
- Used TMDB API to fetch information about movies and tv series in JSON format
- Made API calls using axios npm library.
- Used **Flexbox** for elegantly displaying components.
- Play trailer using **npm** libraries like YouTube, MovieTrailer.

Recipe App

- Designed in React.
- Used an API to gather different food recipes.
- Search option that allows to fill in any specific keyword for recipe finder.
- Displayed recipes in the form of cards to make them look nicer.

Baking Bella

- Developed e-commerce website using MEAN Stack (MongoDB, Express, Angular, Node).
- Designed front-end using **AngularJS** to display a list of products to the user.
- Designed a database in **MongoDB** to store information about products, orders, and users.
- Created **REST API** with routes to display the data using **Node** and **Express**.
- Displayed information about each product with Angular components consuming the REST API.

Geekillus

- Developed e-commerce website in WordPress.
- Used Woo Commerce plugin.
- Created plugin and implemented in web application.

EDUCATION

Web Design & Development (High Distinction) - 3.93 GPA

May 2020 - August 2021

Conestoga Collage, Kitchener, Ontario, Canada

Program Highlights

- Responsive website design
- Web design and development principles
- Database Management
- Frontend and backend development

Master's in Computer Science & engineering – 7.89 OCPA

Aug 2014 – Aug 2016

Punjab Agricultural University, Punjab, India

Program Highlights

- Practical in object-oriented programming
- Advanced Data Structures
- APIs and Database Designing

Bachelor's in Computer Science & engineering - 73.89%

July 2008 – June 2012

Punjab Technical University, Punjab, India

Program Highlights

- Object-oriented programming
- Data Structures
- Logic building and problem-solving
- Database management system